<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perfect relation of the beginning and continuation of the Irish-rebellion, from May last, to this present 12th. of January, 1641. With the place where, and persons who, did plot, contrive, and put in execution that Romish damnable designe. As also their inhumane cruelties which they have, and still execute, with divellish hatred, upon the Protestants. Written by a worthy gentleman and sent over by a merchant now dwelling in Dublin. Whereunto is annexed the merchants letter who sent the copy of this relation: with another letter wherein is truely related, the battell fought betwixt our English, and the rebels, on the tenth of January at a town called Swords, eight miles from Dublin.</title>
            <author>Jones, Henry, 1605-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J942A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E131_35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873525</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873525</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 23:E131[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perfect relation of the beginning and continuation of the Irish-rebellion, from May last, to this present 12th. of January, 1641. With the place where, and persons who, did plot, contrive, and put in execution that Romish damnable designe. As also their inhumane cruelties which they have, and still execute, with divellish hatred, upon the Protestants. Written by a worthy gentleman and sent over by a merchant now dwelling in Dublin. Whereunto is annexed the merchants letter who sent the copy of this relation: with another letter wherein is truely related, the battell fought betwixt our English, and the rebels, on the tenth of January at a town called Swords, eight miles from Dublin.</title>
                  <author>Jones, Henry, 1605-1682.</author>
                  <author>P. G., Merchant now dwelling in Dublin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641 [i.e. 1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The relation was written by "Dean Jones of Kilmore," i.e. Henry Jones, the Bishop of Meath.</note>
                  <note>The merchant's letter signed: P.G.</note>
                  <note>Page 16 is misnumbered 8.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:156350:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A Perfect Relation of THE Beginning and Continuation of the Iriſh-Rebellion, From <hi>May</hi> laſt, to this preſent 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>January,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>With the Place where, and Perſons who, did Plot, Contrive, and put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that Romiſh damnable Deſigne.</p>
            <p>As alſo their inhumane Cruelties which they have, and ſtill execute, with divelliſh hatred, upon the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Written by a worthy Gentleman, and ſent over by a Merchant now dwelling in DUBLIN.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed the Merchants letter who ſent the Copy of this <hi>Relation:</hi> With another letter wherein is truely related, The Battell fought betwixt our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the Rebels, on the tenth of <hi>January,</hi> at a Town called <hi>Swords,</hi> eight Miles from DUBLIN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156350:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:156350:2"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your kind Letter from your friend, whoſe preſence I have not yet had the happineſſe to enjoy; I ſhall ſhew him what curteſie and reſpect I can. I have now herein made bold to trouble you with a Relation written by an honeſt Gentleman of theſe parts. I will paſſe my word the work is truly written, and not like thoſe ſcurrilous things printed concerning this Kingdome. God help us, we are in a miſerable condition, there will be no ſafety here without the deſtruction of vile Popery. Our Armie conſiſting of about 3000. men, is again gone abroad this day to fight with the enemy, God give them good ſucceſſe. Yeſterday they burnt ſome Villages about ſeven miles off that harboured the Rogues, and brought in 3000. Sheep, and 80. Cowes, with other pillage: Our Ships being four ſnall ones, one great one, of a 190. Tuns, are gone
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156350:3"/>
yeſterday well provided to releeve <hi>Droghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dath,</hi> which I hope they have done, the winde being to their deſire. This in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of your news, which I pray impart to our friends. Thus with my hearty good wiſhes to you, and your Wife, I take leave,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very loving friend, <hi>P. G.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:156350:3"/>
               <head>A perfect Relation of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the beginning thereof, till this preſent <hi>Ianuary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce the Iriſh Army in <hi>May</hi> laſt was disbanded, (which was done with much reluctation of the multitude, being very unwilling to lay down their Arms,) and the Romiſh plot for civill Warres (and bloody battell practiſed by the lurking Jeſuits, and their adherents, the Romaniſts in generall) between our gracious Soveraign, and his Subjects of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> tooke none effect; and the opportunity and means of taking away root and branch of the Proteſtants, both <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and <hi>Scotiſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> was avoided. It is clear and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that this new way of Treaſon and Rebellion, was by the diſloyall and perfidious Romaniſts, the Incendiaries of all Chriſtendome, at ſome frequent Conventicles and meetings, principally at a Friary called <hi>Multifornam</hi> in the County of <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> where many hundreds of them met and conſulted for many daies together this laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (proviſion being brought in unto them by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) where they thus plotted, contrived, and put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution as followeth, <hi>videlicet.</hi> That on the 23. day of <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober</hi> laſt, moſt of the Kings Forts and Caſtles throughout the Realm, ſhould be by ſelect men ſet out and allotted to every particular Fort and Caſtle to be by them ſurprized;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156350:4"/>
and the Governours and Keepers thereof ſlain, or kept priſoners.</p>
               <p>Accordingly many Caſtles and Forts were then ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes; the Surprizers under colour of neighbourhood and friendſhip, inviting themſelves to breakfaſt or dinners to the Governors and keepers thereof, where themſelves, their Wives, Children, and Servants were robbed, ſpoiled, and ſtripped of all their monies, plate, jewells, goods, corn, Cattell, Houſholdſtuffe, and Apparell, and ſome ſlain or hanged, and ſome kept priſoners, and barbarouſly handled.</p>
               <p>For ſurpriſall of his Highneſſe principall Caſtle and City of <hi>Dublin;</hi> where the reſidence of this Princely go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is, was allotted and aſſigned the Lord <hi>Macguire</hi> Baron of <hi>Eneskelim,</hi> the two <hi>Macmoghans,</hi> and others. The Lord <hi>Macguire</hi> to that purpoſe repaired to <hi>Dublin</hi> ſome few daies before; and the <hi>Macmoghans,</hi> and the reſt, the two and twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> with intent to ſurpriſe the Caſtle on the morrow at the opening of the Gates, and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe the Draw-bridge, and to act their intended tragicall maſſacre of the Proteſtants, on the twenty fourth day of <hi>October</hi> being Sunday.</p>
               <p>To that purpoſe had they gathered together a multitude of deſperate ſavage barbarous fellowes out of their remote Countries into <hi>Dublin:</hi> of whom (upon the diſcouery of the conſpiracie) the Lord <hi>Macguire,</hi> the <hi>Macmoghans,</hi> and many others were apprehended and tooke the Caſtle the ſame day; but not ſo early in the morning as they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and are yet there in durance. And many hundreds more were neere approaching to the City of <hi>Dublin</hi> on the three and twentieth day of <hi>October;</hi> but upon the noiſe of the diſcovery, Retreated.</p>
               <p>And moreover about foure hundred men having divers Moneths lien on Shipboord in the Port of <hi>Dublin</hi> in two of the beſt Ships furniſhed with Guns, frequenting that Port, hired under pretence of tranſporting thoſe foure hundred men, being levied and Shipped by his Highneſſe Letters of Licence for <hi>Spain</hi> were upon the diſcovery neglected, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156350:4"/>
no further care taken for their tranſportation, or victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. But the Friar, one <hi>Mallun,</hi> that had been the chiefe agent in victualling, and for the pretended tranſportation of thoſe foure hundred men, hid himſelfe from further exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and inquiry; and the men were thereupon ſet on ſhore.</p>
               <p>What the ſecret intended intended Plot was, as well touching thoſe foure hundred men, as alſo touching thoſe two armed Ships, the occurrences and conſequence being compared, I leave to the judicious to diſcern; many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes being made againſt Articles of Charter-party, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Maſters and Navigators of the ſayd Ships from hoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſaile when the winde ſerved. Notwithſtanding, it pleaſed that Almighty and omniſcient God, that hath been alwayes propitious, benigne, and gracious to our gracious King, in reſcuing and delivering him; as alſo his gracious Father of famous memory, and famous Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> their predeceſſor, from many malicious, wicked, and bloody Romiſh deſignes; As the Queen from piſtolls, poiſons, and poniards, and the Armado of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the year 1588. King <hi>James,</hi> and our gracious King <hi>Charles</hi> from the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Treaſon, and ſince, in bringing back our gracious Soveraigne Lord, and King, out of the jawes of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> by defeating, and preventing the maſſacre of his Majeſties Royall Siſter, and her Royall iſſue in <hi>Holland;</hi> from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado, in the year 1639. overthrown by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> without his loſſe or coſts. From inteſtine and civill wars between him and his Subjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> laboured by that Arch-devill, Arch-juggler. So now by his ſecret and mighty power and providence (as the manner of diſcovery will make appeare) to prevent the imminent ruine, and utter deſtruction and loſſe of the whole Realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Highneſſe people the Proteſtants, which muſt have followed; if the Caſtle or <hi>Dublin,</hi> whereby all his Highneſſe ſtores and proviſions of all manner of Arms, Ammunition, and inſtruments for War, being then no ſmall quantity had been ſurpriſed. Yet the reſt of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156350:5"/>
in moſt of the Counties throughout the Realme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confident of the good ſucceſſe of the Lord <hi>Macguire</hi> in ſurpriſing the Caſtle, and City of <hi>Dublin.</hi> (And well they might be confident thereof, for the good ſucceſſe of the Catholike cauſe was prayed for at their Maſſes;) went on with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir traiterous and bloudy reſolutions; and the neighbouring <hi>Iriſh</hi> in moſt Counties, ſlew the neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Debtors their Creditors Tenants their Landlords, ſome Lords of lands their Tenants, Mortgagers their Mortgagees, Servants their Maſters, and ſeverally poſſeſſed themſelves of their ſeverall lands and goods, Money, plate, jewels, apparell, houſholdſtuffe, corn, and cattell, and thruſt them, that they let live, out of doores naked. Many great mens ſervants being <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ran away from their Maſters with their beſt Horſes to the Rebels. The Rebels further proſecuting their traiterous and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious deſignes; ſurpriſed every day more and more of his Highneſſe Forts, Caſtles, and Towns, partly by fraudulent and treacherous inſinuation, partly by force, partly by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of faire quarter to thoſe his Highneſſe Subjects, who had upon the noiſe of the Rebellion betaken themſelves thereunto for ſafegard of themſelves and their goods, that upon rendition they ſhould carry away bag and baggage. Behold, all ye that paſſe by, and read this relation, how theſe promiſes of quarter were performed<hi>!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No ſooner came his Majeſties ſubjects out of thoſe Holds, but they were all, by the Rebells, ſtripped naked; ſome bloodily wounded, even to death, but left alive languiſhing; their bellies being ripped, and guts iſſuing, caſt upon dung-hils; ſome butchered and cut into gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets; ſome men, ſome women hanged, yea many hanged, or otherwiſe put to death by them, when they returned from ſome skirmiſhes with leſſe.</p>
               <p>No degree of Laity, or of, or belonging to the Clergy ſpared; but Ladies, Gentlewomen, women great with childe, yea, children, very infants and ſucklings, as well as men, all robb'd, and ſtripped naked, and expoſed to extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156350:5"/>
of winde and weather, in a cold winter ſeaſon, and forced to lie on the cold earth in the fields, in their travell towards <hi>Dublin;</hi> over whom, being driven together in Herds and Flocks, the Salvages inſulted, and upbraided them, ſaying, Now are ye wilde Iriſh as well as we, and ye may go to <hi>Dublin,</hi> if ye will; but ye will finde little ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour there, for we are ſure the Caſtle and City are taken. Whither thouſands of them repairing from farre, being ſore ſmitten with hunger and cold before they came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; many of them, after ſeverall reliefs upon the high way, having been thrice ſtripped by the unmercifull Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (it is true) found but ſlender ſuccour; for indeed it is not there to be had, howſoever ſome particular men have been very bountifull in their Alms and contribution.</p>
               <p>For the one halfe of the City and Suburbs are Papiſts, and will not, or dare not relieve a Proteſtant for fear of <hi>Romes</hi> curſe, which is denounced againſt them, if they do relieve. Of the other halfe two parts of three, are poore, and not able to give; and halfe a third part are departed with their eſtates into <hi>England</hi> for ſafety; inſomuch as the diſtreſſed poore robbed people dye there on heaps, as before they did in the fields upon their travell.</p>
               <p>It is now little more than two moneths ſince this Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion burſt out, during within, and ſince which time the Traitors and Rebels have ſo beſtirred themſelves, that they have not left an Engliſhman ſubfiſting in any part of the Realm, except in the Province of <hi>Conhaught;</hi> where they are beholding the goodneſſe, loyalty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd fidelity of the noble Earle of <hi>Clenricard,</hi> and the care and vigilancie of the Right Honourable the Preſident of the ſame Province, for their being<hi>:</hi> And in ſome parts of the Provinces of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter;</hi> the firſt whereof is in part planted with Engliſh, being the portion of the noble Earle of <hi>Corke,</hi> and the laſt with <hi>Scots,</hi> being the portion of divers noble and generous <hi>Scots</hi> (who have behaved themſelves bravely, and ſtoutly againſt the Rebels; as alſo ſome of the Engliſh Chiefe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains have, who (I doubt not) ſhall reape the due
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156350:6"/>
merit of their courage and valour;) and in ſome other few fortified Towns, Caſtles, and Forts, able for a while to defend themſelves from the rage and fury of the multitude, who have dared to ſtop up all the high-wayes and paſſages from <hi>Dublin</hi> to remote parts, thereby to prevent all poſtage of Letters, and meſſages from the State to any Town, City, or County, Governour, Lievetenant, or Commander, to lay ambuſhes for his Highn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe Forces, Men, Arms, and Ammunition, and to ſurpriſe the Arms, and ſlay the men, to rob and ſpoile all the Engliſh within two myles of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and to bring up their forces ſo neere, and to skirmiſh with his Highneſſe Forces, they having gotten at leaſt 3000, or 4000 Arms of his Majeſties by force, or fraud, but moſt by treachery.</p>
               <p>They have dared above a whole moneth to beſiege his Majeſties Towne of <hi>Drogheda,</hi> both by Sea and Land, the ſame being but twenty miles remote from <hi>Dublin;</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as both Towns are already ſtraightned for victuals<hi>: Drogheda</hi> having had for all that time no market at all, and <hi>Dublin</hi> a very ſlender and thin market; therein appeering now ſcarcely either pound of freſh butter, or cheeſe, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key, Gooſe, Hen, Capon, Chick, Egge, or Pigge, or any manner of Sea-foul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and little Fiſh; all which were wont to be very plentifull, and at cheape rates. It is ſuppoſed that moſt of the Fiſher-men are become Rebels. The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Corn, Beife, Mutton, Veale, and Porke are already doubled to that they were at the begining of the Rebellion. For in very deed, the Rebels have ſurpriſed, or do detaine from market, or are poſſeſſed of all the Corn and Cattle almoſt in the whole Realm.</p>
               <p>At the firſt, and for one moneths ſpace after the Treaſon and Rebellion brake out; it ſeemed to be none other, but ſuch as was plotted, ſtirred, and enterprized only by ſome Male-contented old <hi>Iriſh,</hi> againſt the Engliſh; whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors and themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed their Anceſtors lands, and Revenues, and the cauſe not Romiſh, and univerſall; but it had been poſſible to have been conceived, that if the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156350:6"/>
Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi> had been ſurpriſed; the cauſe would have proved not onely diſcontent for diſ-inheritance, but the Catholike Romiſh cauſe a Kingdome, and a new Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like King.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as thoſe of the vicinity of <hi>Dublin,</hi> Lords, knights and Gentlemen of the Pale, the old Engliſh, had by their cautelous inſinuations, and proteſtations of loyalty and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to the King, and Crowne, ſeverally obtained from the Right Honourable, the Lords, Juſtices, ſeverall Arms and Ammunition out of his Highneſſe Store-houſe, in his Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> for their pretended private defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rebels: and had afterwards declared themſelves, by laying aſide thoſe ſeverall Arms and Ammunition toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for a publike offence againſt our Soveraigne Lord the King, his Crowne and dignity, to be their confederates, Then it apperred manifeſtly that the cauſe was not only private diſcontent of ſome particular men, but Univerſall, Romiſh, and devilliſh, even for a Kingdom. For what did, or could the laſt Committee of Parliament crave of his Highneſſe for enlargement of their juriſdictions, immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and liberties, which was not liberally of his free Grace granted. Let the whole World behold, and ſee the free Grace, and bounty, of a Royall, Virtuous, and pious King; and the diſloyall ingratitude, and heatheniſh immanity, of a perfidious, and Rebellious people, who have ſo Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly requited his King-like clemency and benignity. For they have not only deſtroyed, and made deſolate his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in two moneths, which hath been fourty years im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting ſince the laſt civill Wars; but they have alſo rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed him of his Rents, Revenues, and Cuſtomes, and part of thoſe Subſidies which themſelves had helped to confirm by Act of Parliament, and robbed, ſpoiled, and murthered many of his Liege-people, which ſhould, and would have cheerfully payed thoſe Subſidies. For they have deſtroyed all Merchandize and Trade throughout the Realm, wherby even many of themſelves, and their impions faction, muſt of neceſſity ſuffer infinitely; millions of gold will not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156350:7"/>
countervail the dammage on all ſides. One thing more in particular, touching thoſe of the Pale neer the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the confines is worthy to be related, <hi>videlicet,</hi> that when ſome of them had obtained Arms, and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition for 500. men, with pretence to reſiſt the Rebels: beſides thoſe a forementioned for their private defence, they returned anſwer, that they could not levy ſo many men, who would fight againſt the Rebels: and therefore they would return the Arms, and Ammunition, and ſo did, but not to the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> whence they received them, but to the Town <hi>Droghedath,</hi> which is now beſieged, between which and <hi>Dublin,</hi> the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me men nowly with an Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, expecting doubtleſſe, ſhortly to have all thoſe Arms again.</p>
               <p>For the beſt of them, who appeared moſt in getting forth thoſe Armes, have ſince refuſed to come in upon Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y have joyned themſelves with the Rebels, they have taken the Kings Subjects priſoners, they have again r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leaſed them, and given them paſſes from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iriſh Army, coloured with pretended authority in the Kings Name, with their own names, and a Romiſh Prieſts, or Fry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs ſubſcribed. Was not this a neat Romiſh trick? Let all theſe conveyances, and occurrences be laid together, and then let all the Princes, and Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> judge, and cenſure, whether Religion can warrant ſuch fraud, and treachery, treaſon, and rebellion, robbery, ſpoil, rapine, bloudy cruelty, and murders.</p>
               <p>The primitive perſecutions were exquiſite torments of divers kindes full of tyranny, and cruelty; but they were ſhort, and made a ſpeedy end of life; but this new found way of perſecution by cold, and hunger, much more terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and exceedeth them all, becauſe it is a long lingring, and languiſhing torment, and ſo much the more cruell, becauſe exerciſed on women, yea women great with childe, Infants, and Sucklings.</p>
               <p>Theſe tyrants, and bloudy minded men, certainly are not Kings, nor Governours; by what authority then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156350:7"/>
they ſuch cruelty upon their fellow Subjects? What can they ſay for themſelves, if they ſhould anſwer before their King? If they pretend religion, though there be a mulct of ninepence, each Sabbath upon every perſon of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent age abſenting himſelf from Divine Service by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Law enacted in the Realm, they cannot alledge that it was put in execution, or that they had not freedom for their Romiſh ſuperſtitions, which to endeavor to convince them of by argument is but folly. For their pretended Catholike cauſe, which already appeareth to be the mother of treaſon, and rebellion, the ſin of witchcraft, murder, and all other abominations, and will ſhortly appear, even to themſelves to be the daughter of Antichriſt, and Antichriſtianiſme, muſt by an inevitable divine decree, be convinced by fire, and ſword. Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name give the glory, for thy loving mercy; and for thy truths ſake.</p>
               <p>For if the Lord himſelf had not been on our ſide, now may we, that ſurvive ſince the day of diſcovery of their abominable treaſon, and rebellion, ſay, when they roſe up againſt us; they had ſwallowed us up quick, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were ſo wrathfully diſpleaſed at us. Praiſed be the Lord, which hath not given us over as a prey unto their teeth. The ſnare is broken, and we are delivered. It may be collected that King <hi>David,</hi> in theſe precedent words of his, prophecied of theſe later times, and the Romiſh perſecution. For how were the ſnares broken, and we delivered, when there was but tenne houres left unrun out from catching us in their ſnare? Meerly by the providence of God, as the many formerly mentioned deliverances were. It appeareth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, that the conſpiracy had been long in hatching, and contriving with true Romiſh ſecrecy. For the honeſt man <hi>Owen O-Connely,</hi> the diſcoverer being an Iriſh man, but a Proteſtant (as he hath declared to divers of his familiar friends) having obſerved by diſcourſe among the Iriſh, that there was ſome enterprize in hand prayed for, at their Maſſes, in furtherance, and good ſucceſſe of the Catholike
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156350:8"/>
cauſe, Although he had diſſembled his Religion, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented their Maſſes in places remote from his habitation, where he was not known, could never obtain a true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the particular, untill the very evening of the two and twentieth day of <hi>October,</hi> when <hi>Hugh Mac-Moghan,</hi> one of the conſpirators, intending to expreſſe his love to <hi>Owen O Connely,</hi> and to reſcue him out of the approaching danger, and to that end having invited him by Letters, and an expreſſe Meſſenger to ride with him a long journey to <hi>Dublin,</hi> upon earneſt affairs, they with the reſt being thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come; opening his minde to <hi>Owen,</hi> told him what the enterpriſe was, <hi>videlicet,</hi> the ſurprizall of the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and Maſſacre of the Proteſtants, and enjoyned him ſecrecy, and fidelity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owen</hi> could do no leſſe for his own ſafeties ſake, then give conſent, and promiſe fidelity, and ſecrecy. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he diſwaded <hi>Hugh Mac-Moghan</hi> from the enterprize, but did not prevail. For <hi>Hugh Mac-Moghan</hi> anſwered, that it was too farre gone, he was ſo deepely engaged, that he had vowed perſeverance, or to that effect. If it be ſo, replied <hi>Owen,</hi> let us go on, I will do my beſt, or to that effect.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding his verball conſent, the good man moved with the fear of God, love of his King and Country, and commiſeration of his fellow Subjects, Chriſtians, and Proteſtants, whom he well ſaw, and knew were ſure to be loſt, and ruined if the plot ſucceeded, wiſely reſerving to himſelf his compunction of heart, and loyall affection, kept company with the Traytors, ahd revelled with them in Taverns, untill he had drunk too much; but in the end watching his opportunity, ſlipt away, from them, into one of the Lords Juſtices houſes, and diſcovered unto the Lord Juſtice the conſpiracy; to which the Lord Juſtice gave little credence at firſt, becauſe he perceived that <hi>Owen</hi> had drunk too much. But the vehemency, and importunity of <hi>Owen,</hi> moved him to embrace, and take the information to heart, and immediately it being then late in the night to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156350:8"/>
go to councell with his Peers, and to take courſe for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of that wicked, and damnable Treaſon, and for apprehenſion of the conſpirators, who were eight or nine of them attached, within eight or nine houres after; a little before the prefixed hour of their intended miſchief, and the Lord <hi>Macguire</hi> about the midſt of the ſame day.</p>
               <p>For every particular of the manner of diſcovery, it is not materiall to ſet out; <hi>Owen O-Conney</hi> beſt can, and hath already told his own tale.</p>
               <p>Herein is given only a brief touch of it, whereout may be gathered, that the finger of God was in it, in framing the heart of <hi>Hugh Mac-Moghan</hi> towards <hi>Owen O-Connely,</hi> and to diſcover that to him in the very point of time, which he had ſo buſily, and induſtriouſly long ſought after. Therefore let glory be given to God the principall diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Dated at <hi>Dublin</hi> 
                     <date>the fourth of <hi>January.</hi> 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>By the laſt weeks P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſte I writ unto you, certifying you of our lamentable condition, craving your favourable advice, and charitable helpe in our affairs; whereof I doubt not, it being Gods cauſe, and our dear Countries, for which we all ſuffer. I have herein ſent a Letter from a very good friend of mine, and kinſman, Maſter <hi>Dean Jones,</hi> of <hi>Kilmore,</hi> who hath miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly eſcaped with life: Of which I humbly crave the carefull delivery to our worthy K. Attorney.</p>
               <p>As for our affaires in generall, or otherwiſe, here is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156350:9"/>
no difference or amendment ſince my laſt; only, I thought meet to write unto you a ſhort relation of our late skirmiſh. On mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day night laſt, we ſent out a Party of about 2000 foot, and 200 horſe, to a Town called <hi>Swords,</hi> eight myles off; where they came about ſix of the clocke next morning, and found the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, being a thouſand men, Intrenched in the Town, on whom they ſhot for the ſpace of halfe an houre; and at laſt brakè in upon the Trenches, but found ſtrong oppoſition. But our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Party coming another way upon them, put them to flight; and purſuing them about halfe a myle, reterned, plundered the Town. Our new Engliſh Souldiers ſpared neither man, woman, or childe therein, they got ſtore of good booty; among which, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 400 Cowes, a great part whereof ſhould that morning have been killed for the Rogues breakefaſt, they expecting a ſupply: Our men alſo tooke four Colours, and ſlew in the Towne and purſuit 179 men, beſides thoſe the Enemy conveyed away du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the fight, on horſebacke, and otherwiſe, whoſe number or quality is not yet known: The Town alſo was burnt, and great ſtore of Corn unthraſhed. But alas! our victory is nothing, if we conſider the loſſe of a brave Spirit on our part, Sir <hi>Lorenzo Cary,</hi> brother to the Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> who with three more were killed in the fight on our part. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill we have a good ſupply we are able to do little, which God ſend unto us ſpeedily, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us till then, and evermore.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Laus Deo.</hi> In <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                     <date>Jan. 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your humble and affectionate ſervant, <hi>P. G.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
